<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"
	xmlns:itunes="http://www.itunes.com/dtds/podcast-1.0.dtd"
	xmlns:googleplay="http://www.google.com/schemas/play-podcasts/1.0">
	<channel>
		<title>
			<![CDATA[D. E. Williams + Co. Insights]]>
		</title>
		<description>
			<![CDATA[Thoughts, ideas, and ramblings on tech, culture, and public policy]]>
		</description>
		<link>https://dewilliamsco.substack.com</link>
		<image>
			<url>https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_256,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fdewilliamsco.substack.com%2Fimg%2Fsubstack.png</url>
			<title>D. E. Williams + Co. Insights</title>
			<link>https://dewilliamsco.substack.com</link>
		</image>
		<generator>Substack</generator>
		<lastBuildDate>Sat, 03 May 2025 14:46:59 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<atom:link href="https://dewilliamsco.substack.com/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
		<copyright>
			<![CDATA[Daniel Williams]]>
		</copyright>
		<language>
			<![CDATA[en]]>
		</language>
		<webMaster>
			<![CDATA[dewilliamsco@substack.com]]>
		</webMaster>
		<itunes:owner>
			<itunes:email>
				<![CDATA[dewilliamsco@substack.com]]>
			</itunes:email>
			<itunes:name>
				<![CDATA[Daniel Williams]]>
			</itunes:name>
		</itunes:owner>
		<itunes:author>
			<![CDATA[Daniel Williams]]>
		</itunes:author>
		<googleplay:owner>
			<![CDATA[dewilliamsco@substack.com]]>
		</googleplay:owner>
		<googleplay:email>
			<![CDATA[dewilliamsco@substack.com]]>
		</googleplay:email>
		<googleplay:author>
			<![CDATA[Daniel Williams]]>
		</googleplay:author>
		<item>
			<title>
				<![CDATA[My 5-Day Gen AI Intensive Experience]]>
			</title>
			<description>
				<![CDATA[From Novice to Builder]]>
			</description>
			<link>https://dewilliamsco.substack.com/p/my-5-day-gen-ai-intensive-experience</link>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">https://dewilliamsco.substack.com/p/my-5-day-gen-ai-intensive-experience</guid>
			<dc:creator>
				<![CDATA[Daniel Williams]]>
			</dc:creator>
			<pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 15:33:35 GMT</pubDate>
			<content:encoded>
				<![CDATA[<p>Between March 31 and April 4, 2025, I had the opportunity to participate in an intensive 5-day course focused on the fascinating world of Generative AI. As someone eager to delve deeper into this transformative technology, the course proved to be an invaluable experience, providing a comprehensive overview of key concepts and practical skills. This article will outline my journey through the intensive, highlight the main takeaways, and briefly describe the capstone projects I developed, showcasing how they integrate the lessons learned.</p><p>Everyone knows what Google is, but if you&#8217;re unfamiliar with Kaggle, it is an ML platform (acquired by Google) that sponsors ML and AI competitions. For example, companies, government agencies, nonprofits, and research organizations can host competitions to solve problems using machine learning and AI on the Kaggle platform. The winners typically win cash prizes for solving the problem or making significant progress towards a solution.</p><div class="subscription-widget-wrap-editor" data-attrs="{&quot;url&quot;:&quot;https://dewilliamsco.substack.com/subscribe?&quot;,&quot;text&quot;:&quot;Subscribe&quot;,&quot;language&quot;:&quot;en&quot;}" data-component-name="SubscribeWidgetToDOM"><div class="subscription-widget show-subscribe"><div class="preamble"><p class="cta-caption">Thanks for reading The Idea Room Newsletter! Subscribe for free to receive new posts and support my work.</p></div><form class="subscription-widget-subscribe"><input type="email" class="email-input" name="email" placeholder="Type your email&#8230;" tabindex="-1"><input type="submit" class="button primary" value="Subscribe"><div class="fake-input-wrapper"><div class="fake-input"></div><div class="fake-button"></div></div></form></div></div><p>What made this 5-day course interesting were 2 things: </p><ol><li><p><strong>The course was 100% free for everyone.</strong> All you had to do was register, attend the livestreams on YouTube, complete the daily hands-on assignments, and submit a capstone project incorporating everything we learned over the week.</p></li><li><p>The course was taught by researchers and engineers from Google, Kaggle, and DeepMind (the leading AI research lab in the world, also acquired by Google).</p></li></ol><h3>Recent Advances in Gen AI: Laying the Foundation</h3><p>The course kicked off by exploring the <strong>"Foundational Large Language Models &amp; Text Generation"</strong>. We delved into the evolution of these models, starting from the early transformer architectures and tracing the lineage through models like <strong>GPT-1, BERT, GPT-2, Gopher, PaLM, and culminating in Google's state-of-the-art Gemini family</strong>. The advancements highlighted were significant, including <strong>Gemini's multimodal capabilities</strong>, allowing it to process interleaved sequences of text, image, audio, and video. We learned about the crucial role of <strong>unsupervised pre-training on massive datasets</strong> like BooksCorpus and WebText, which enables these models to learn intricate language patterns. The discussion also touched upon techniques like <strong>fine-tuning</strong> to adapt LLMs to specific tasks or domains and methods for <strong>accelerating inference</strong> to make these powerful models more practical. The emergence of models like <strong>Mistral, OpenAI's "o1" series, DeepSeek, Yi, and Grok</strong> further showcased the competitive and innovative landscape of LLMs.</p><h3>What Was Taught and Learned: A Daily Breakdown</h3><p>The course was structured to provide a comprehensive learning journey over five days:</p><ul><li><p><strong>Day 1: Prompt Engineering and Evaluation</strong>: We mastered the <strong>"art of prompt engineering for optimal LLM interaction"</strong>, understanding how different parameters can influence the output. Crucially, we learned how to <strong>evaluate LLM responses</strong> using autoraters and by structuring the output effectively. We completed codelabs on <strong>prompting fundamentals</strong> and <strong>evaluation with structured data</strong>.</p></li><li><p><strong>Day 2: Embeddings and Vector Stores/Databases</strong>: This day focused on the <strong>conceptual underpinnings of embeddings</strong> and their geometric power for classifying and comparing textual data. We explored <strong>vector databases</strong> and how they enable bringing live or specialized data into LLM applications, forming the basis of <strong>Retrieval-Augmented Generation (RAG) systems</strong>. Codelabs included <strong>building a RAG question-answering system</strong>, exploring <strong>text similarity with embeddings</strong>, and creating a <strong>neural classification network with Keras using embeddings</strong>. We learned that Vertex AI text embeddings can be used with the Vertex AI SDK, Langchain, and BigQuery for embedding and advanced workflows.</p></li><li><p><strong>Day 3: Generative AI Agents</strong>: We learned how to build <strong>sophisticated AI agents</strong> by understanding their core components and the iterative development process. Key concepts included <strong>function calling</strong> to connect LLMs to external systems and the real world, and building <strong>multi-agent systems using LangGraph</strong>. The codelabs involved <strong>talking to a database with function calling</strong> and building an <strong>agentic ordering system in LangGraph</strong>.</p></li><li><p><strong>Day 4: Domain-Specific LLMs</strong>: This unit explored the creation and application of <strong>specialized LLMs</strong> like SecLM for cybersecurity and MedLM for healthcare. We learned how to <strong>fine-tune a Gemini model for custom tasks</strong> using our own labeled data and how to <strong>use Google Search data in generation</strong>.</p></li><li><p><strong>Day 5: MLOps for Generative AI</strong>: The final day focused on <strong>adapting MLOps practices for Generative AI</strong>, including leveraging tools like Vertex AI for foundation models and generative AI applications, particularly <strong>AgentOps for agentic applications</strong>. We explored the goo.gle/agent-starter-pack repository to understand how to make MLOps for Gen AI easier and accelerate the path to production.</p></li></ul><h3>Empowering the Next Generation of AI Builders Goes Beyond Just AI Models</h3><p>The 5-Day Gen AI Intensive provided several key takeaways that have significantly enhanced my understanding and ability to work with Generative AI:</p><ul><li><p><strong>The Power and Flexibility of LLMs:</strong> I gained a profound appreciation for the capabilities of LLMs, from text generation and summarization to question-answering and even code generation. The multimodality of models like Gemini was particularly impressive.</p></li><li><p><strong>The power of embeddings and RAG</strong>: Integrating external knowledge through embeddings and RAG is vital for building grounded and reliable LLM applications.</p></li><li><p><strong>The Importance of Prompt Engineering:</strong> I learned that carefully crafted prompts are crucial for eliciting the desired behavior from LLMs. Understanding different prompting strategies is key to unlocking their full potential.</p></li><li><p><strong>Fine-tuning for Specialization:</strong> The course highlighted the effectiveness of fine-tuning pre-trained models to achieve superior performance on specific tasks or within particular domains. This allows for building specialized AI solutions without the need for training from scratch.</p></li><li><p><strong>The Agentic Future:</strong> I was particularly excited by the concept of AI agents &#8211; autonomous systems that can reason, act using tools, and achieve goals. This paradigm opens up a vast array of possibilities for building intelligent applications.</p></li><li><p><strong>Evaluation is Crucial:</strong> The intensive emphasized the importance of rigorous evaluation throughout the development lifecycle of Gen AI applications. Understanding how to assess the quality, safety, and reliability of LLM outputs is paramount.</p></li><li><p><strong>The Necessity of MLOps for Gen AI</strong>: Moving beyond proofs-of-concept to production-ready Gen AI applications requires a strong foundation in MLOps and increasingly, AgentOps.</p></li><li><p><strong>The value of domain-specific LLMs</strong>: Fine-tuning models or using specialized models like SecLM and MedLM can significantly improve performance in specific areas.</p></li></ul><h3>Potential Capstone Projects: Applying the Lessons Learned</h3><p>To solidify my understanding and apply the knowledge gained during the intensive, I embarked on three potential capstone projects:</p><ol><li><p><strong>Interactive Smart Home Control:</strong> This project, available <a href="https://github.com/danieleugenewilliams/interactive-smart-home">here</a>, focuses on simulating the control of a virtual smart home environment using a chat interface powered by an LLM. By installing <code>langchain-google-genai</code> and running a Jupyter notebook, users can send natural language commands (e.g., "Turn on kitchen lights") and receive feedback on the updated home state. This project directly incorporates the lessons on <strong>leveraging LLMs for natural language understanding and interaction</strong>, as well as the fundamental concepts of building <strong>AI agents that can take actions</strong> (controlling virtual devices) based on user input. The use of <code>langchain-google-genai</code>suggests the application of tools to extend the LLM's capabilities.</p></li><li><p><strong>Multi-Agent Life Advisor:</strong> The second project, found <a href="https://github.com/danieleugenewilliams/multi-agent-advisor">here</a>, creates an interactive "board of advisors" with specialized agents for career and money, built using LangGraph. These agents collaborate to provide personalized, actionable advice tailored to user goals, utilizing <strong>Retrieval-Augmented Generation (RAG)</strong> grounded in relevant knowledge sources. This project directly applies the principles of <strong>multi-agent systems</strong>, where different agents with specific roles work together to solve a complex problem. The use of LangGraph demonstrates an understanding of how to orchestrate workflows between multiple agents. The incorporation of RAG highlights the importance of grounding LLM outputs in reliable information. The project also includes optional user evaluation of the advice, reflecting the course's emphasis on <strong>evaluation</strong>.</p></li><li><p><strong>Private Acquisition Research Automation:</strong> My third project, located <a href="https://github.com/danieleugenewilliams/private-acquisition-automation">here</a>, aims to automate the research process for small business acquisitions by parsing text from business-for-sale listings (OCR'd PDFs) and using Generative AI to extract and analyze financial data. The project utilizes <code>@tool</code> stubs for data extraction and analysis, outputting structured JSON with insights. This project demonstrates the application of <strong>Gen AI for specific domain tasks</strong>(financial data extraction and analysis), as discussed in the context of SecLM and MedLM. Using <code>@tool</code> stubs aligns with the concept of equipping agents with specific functionalities. The focus on extracting structured output showcases an understanding of making LLM outputs more usable for downstream applications.</p></li></ol><p>Overall, the 5-Day Gen AI Intensive provided me with a solid foundation in the principles and practices of Generative AI. The knowledge and skills I gained were instrumental in developing these capstone projects, which I believe effectively demonstrate my ability to apply LLMs and related technologies to solve real-world problems. I am excited to continue exploring the vast potential of Gen AI and build even more innovative applications in the future.</p><div class="subscription-widget-wrap-editor" data-attrs="{&quot;url&quot;:&quot;https://dewilliamsco.substack.com/subscribe?&quot;,&quot;text&quot;:&quot;Subscribe&quot;,&quot;language&quot;:&quot;en&quot;}" data-component-name="SubscribeWidgetToDOM"><div class="subscription-widget show-subscribe"><div class="preamble"><p class="cta-caption">Thanks for reading The Idea Room Newsletter! Subscribe for free to receive new posts and support my work.</p></div><form class="subscription-widget-subscribe"><input type="email" class="email-input" name="email" placeholder="Type your email&#8230;" tabindex="-1"><input type="submit" class="button primary" value="Subscribe"><div class="fake-input-wrapper"><div class="fake-input"></div><div class="fake-button"></div></div></form></div></div>]]>
			</content:encoded>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>
				<![CDATA[Free Speech on the Internet is Broken]]>
			</title>
			<description>
				<![CDATA[Why platforms like X, FB, and TikTok degrade public discourse, and what can be done to make the Web a better platform for the future]]>
			</description>
			<link>https://dewilliamsco.substack.com/p/free-speech-on-the-internet-is-broken</link>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">https://dewilliamsco.substack.com/p/free-speech-on-the-internet-is-broken</guid>
			<dc:creator>
				<![CDATA[Daniel Williams]]>
			</dc:creator>
			<pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 03:48:05 GMT</pubDate>
			<enclosure url="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7501f26f-d1a8-480b-93ef-9ecfb818b8b9_1260x720.png" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
			<content:encoded>
				<![CDATA[<div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2 is-viewable-img" target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7501f26f-d1a8-480b-93ef-9ecfb818b8b9_1260x720.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM"><div class="image2-inset"><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7501f26f-d1a8-480b-93ef-9ecfb818b8b9_1260x720.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7501f26f-d1a8-480b-93ef-9ecfb818b8b9_1260x720.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7501f26f-d1a8-480b-93ef-9ecfb818b8b9_1260x720.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7501f26f-d1a8-480b-93ef-9ecfb818b8b9_1260x720.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7501f26f-d1a8-480b-93ef-9ecfb818b8b9_1260x720.png" width="1260" height="720" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/7501f26f-d1a8-480b-93ef-9ecfb818b8b9_1260x720.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:720,&quot;width&quot;:1260,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:&quot;Free Speech on the Internet is Broken&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:false,&quot;topImage&quot;:true,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false,&quot;align&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt="Free Speech on the Internet is Broken" title="Free Speech on the Internet is Broken" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7501f26f-d1a8-480b-93ef-9ecfb818b8b9_1260x720.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7501f26f-d1a8-480b-93ef-9ecfb818b8b9_1260x720.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7501f26f-d1a8-480b-93ef-9ecfb818b8b9_1260x720.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7501f26f-d1a8-480b-93ef-9ecfb818b8b9_1260x720.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" fetchpriority="high"></picture><div class="image-link-expand"></div></div></a></figure></div><p>The last twenty years have seen the rapid growth of social media platforms, from the early days of GeoCities, Friendster, and MySpace to billion-dollar modern platforms. Instagram, TikTok, Snapchat, LinkedIn, and X. These technologies have allowed us to stay connected throughout school, careers, family events, and even natural disasters. Thanks to the Internet and social media, societies have never been more like Facebook. At the same time, we&#8217;ve never been more disconnected from the real world and real people. </p><p class="button-wrapper" data-attrs="{&quot;url&quot;:&quot;https://dewilliamsco.substack.com/subscribe?&quot;,&quot;text&quot;:&quot;Subscribe now&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:null,&quot;class&quot;:null}" data-component-name="ButtonCreateButton"><a class="button primary" href="https://dewilliamsco.substack.com/subscribe?"><span>Subscribe now</span></a></p><p>Many books have been written on the impact of social media on the brains of children and adults. In Coddling of the American Mind, authors Greg Lukianoff and Jonathan Haidt delve deep into the effects of social media and smartphones on brain development, with the authors recommending that parents protect their children from access to these technologies until well into their teens. We&#8217;ve seen content posted to X on the heels of Christmas 2024 about the real challenges of U.S. immigration. Many of these threads devolved into very bigoted ideas being pushed and promoted. On any given day, you can find some of the most vile content about every demographic on every platform, all in the name of &#8220;Free Speech.&#8221; </p><p>Some will say social media and smartphones have made public discourse worse. However, these technologies simply mirror the morals and ethics of the societies that use them. We saw this in previous eras and media such as radio and television. When television went mainstream, the social mores of society still held to its Christian roots, with the avoidance of gratuitous profanity, sex, and violence. As society began to relax objective morality due to multiple influences in policy, education, and laws, so did the decrease in decorum in the movies and television.</p><p>Internet and social media platforms have followed a similar downward trajectory. As societal morals have nearly evaporated in many areas, we&#8217;ve seen an increase in vile content to match society. Because we are so interconnected through these platforms, the destruction of morals is not contained in their origin. Far-flung remote societies are digitally caught in the net of moral decay as their people are exposed and get hooked on the steady stream of lewd photos, videos, discussions, and violence. Social media platforms have turned vile content into a business model by paying content creators who can post the most viral content, no matter how debaucherous, untrue, or demeaning.</p><p>Social platforms have tried censoring its worst offenders, but others simply pop up in their place. Bot farms emerged nearly a decade ago and have become more sophisticated regarding viral content and user targeting. In many ways, the platforms can&#8217;t fix this issue themselves because they are in the business of viral content. You can&#8217;t police your way to better morals. What is the answer to making the Web and Social Media better for the future? </p><p>Our society&#8217;s ethics, morals, and virtues must change. If we don&#8217;t figure out how to fix our morals, not only will social media continue to get worse, but society will continue to devolve into more chaos, sectarianism, degeneracy, and hate, creating an unvirtuous cycle. </p><p>In my studies into the rise and fall of empires over the last couple of years, a theme has emerged, showing why and how societies devolve and eventually collapse. </p><ol><li><p>Society becomes successful and safe for individuals.</p></li><li><p>Over time, society no longer believes faith in God is essential.</p></li><li><p>Objective morality morphs into relative morality, including truth (i.e., &#8220;my truth&#8221;).</p></li><li><p>Individuals prefer to focus on happiness, wants, and desires at the expense of everything else.</p></li><li><p>Individuals abandon everything that made society great (morals, virtues, ethics, and culture), even at the expense of their society&#8217;s well-being.</p></li></ol><p>This is a crude overview, but it shows the tension between individuals and society that grows when faith, morals, ethics, and culture are abandoned (or replaced), leading to societal decay. <strong>The question is whether this process can be reversed before it is too late.</strong> I believe it can be reversed, but I don&#8217;t know how.</p><div class="captioned-button-wrap" data-attrs="{&quot;url&quot;:&quot;https://dewilliamsco.substack.com/p/free-speech-on-the-internet-is-broken?utm_source=substack&utm_medium=email&utm_content=share&action=share&quot;,&quot;text&quot;:&quot;Share&quot;}" data-component-name="CaptionedButtonToDOM"><div class="preamble"><p class="cta-caption">Thanks for reading The Idea Room Newsletter! This post is public, so feel free to share it.</p></div><p class="button-wrapper" data-attrs="{&quot;url&quot;:&quot;https://dewilliamsco.substack.com/p/free-speech-on-the-internet-is-broken?utm_source=substack&utm_medium=email&utm_content=share&action=share&quot;,&quot;text&quot;:&quot;Share&quot;}" data-component-name="ButtonCreateButton"><a class="button primary" href="https://dewilliamsco.substack.com/p/free-speech-on-the-internet-is-broken?utm_source=substack&utm_medium=email&utm_content=share&action=share"><span>Share</span></a></p></div>]]>
			</content:encoded>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>
				<![CDATA[The Decline of Human Energy - Part I: The Shift in Cultural Dynamics]]>
			</title>
			<description>
				<![CDATA[Why we are losing the power to reason, create, and reflect]]>
			</description>
			<link>https://dewilliamsco.substack.com/p/the-decline-of-human-energy-part</link>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">https://dewilliamsco.substack.com/p/the-decline-of-human-energy-part</guid>
			<dc:creator>
				<![CDATA[Daniel Williams]]>
			</dc:creator>
			<pubDate>Sat, 27 Apr 2024 19:38:57 GMT</pubDate>
			<enclosure url="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F61af7482-da16-464b-9c1c-81bc273e250e_400x400.jpeg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
			<content:encoded>
				<![CDATA[<p>This is Part 1 of a four-part series on The Decline of Human Energy.</p><h2><strong>Introduction</strong></h2><p><strong>Overview</strong>: In recent decades, a profound shift in societal values has emerged, marked by a move away from objective morality and disciplined living towards a landscape dominated by subjective morality and hedonism. This cultural transformation has profound implications, not least of which is a noticeable decline in what can be described as human energy&#8212;the essential capacity to reason, create, and reflect. Traditionally anchored in steadfast moral frameworks and bolstered by communal standards of behavior, this vital energy has fueled the engine of innovation and the reflective depths of philosophical and artistic achievement throughout history. However, as modern societies increasingly embrace relativism and self-indulgence, the foundational pillars that support intellectual vigor and creative pursuits are being eroded. This decline is not merely about a loss of societal cohesion but reflects a deeper erosion of the personal drive and mental acuity necessary for progress and introspection.</p><div class="subscription-widget-wrap-editor" data-attrs="{&quot;url&quot;:&quot;https://dewilliamsco.substack.com/subscribe?&quot;,&quot;text&quot;:&quot;Subscribe&quot;,&quot;language&quot;:&quot;en&quot;}" data-component-name="SubscribeWidgetToDOM"><div class="subscription-widget show-subscribe"><div class="preamble"><p class="cta-caption">Thanks for reading The Idea Room Newsletter! Subscribe for free to receive new posts and support my work.</p></div><form class="subscription-widget-subscribe"><input type="email" class="email-input" name="email" placeholder="Type your email&#8230;" tabindex="-1"><input type="submit" class="button primary" value="Subscribe"><div class="fake-input-wrapper"><div class="fake-input"></div><div class="fake-button"></div></div></form></div></div><p>Philosophers and theologians like St. Augustine and St. Thomas Aquinas have long argued that moral clarity derived from an objective standard is crucial for full intellectual and spiritual development. In parallel, anthropological studies by figures such as J.D. Unwin have empirically linked the vitality of civilizations to their adherence to strict moral codes, particularly in terms of sexual restraint. Furthermore, G.K. Chesterton&#8217;s critiques of modern pride and the abandonment of humility underscore an additional dimension where the inflated self distorts both perception and output. The collective departure from these disciplined paths towards a more selfish and pleasure-seeking existence has diminished our capacity to tackle complex problems creatively and stunted our collective ability to reflect on deeper truths, ultimately stalling personal and societal evolution. As we delve deeper into the consequences of this shift, it becomes imperative to examine the outcomes and underlying choices that drive our current trajectory.</p><h2><strong>Historical and Philosophical Foundations</strong></h2><h4><strong>St. Augustine on Objective Morality</strong></h4><p>St. Augustine, one of the seminal figures in developing Western Christianity and philosophy, steadfastly championed the necessity of objective moral laws grounded in faith in God. For Augustine, these moral laws were not arbitrary but were essential for aligning human nature with its divine purpose and the greater order of the universe. According to his theological system, as outlined in works like &#8220;City of God,&#8221; true freedom and energy&#8212;both personal and communal&#8212;are only achieved through submission to God&#8217;s eternal laws. He argued that when societies adhere to these divine precepts, they cultivate virtues like justice, prudence, and fortitude, which are critical for maintaining societal order and harmony.</p><p>However, Augustine also warned of the dire consequences when societies stray from this path. The abandonment of objective morality in favor of subjective interpretations and desires leads to what he termed a &#8220;disordered love.&#8221; This disorientation manifests in moral chaos and a tangible depletion of energy within the community. As virtues give way to vices, the societal fabric begins to fray, and individuals lose the moral clarity that energizes purposeful action. The result is a community less capable of reasoning, creating, and reflecting deeply, as its members are increasingly driven by base desires rather than guided by transcendent truths.</p><p>Augustine&#8217;s insights underscore a critical aspect of the modern decline in human energy. The shift towards subjective morality and the erosion of disciplined living reflect a broader move away from the structured, purpose-driven life that Augustine posited as ideal. This degradation of societal and individual vitality sets the stage for exploring further philosophical underpinnings with St. Thomas Aquinas, who builds upon Augustinian thought with his profound synthesis of Christian theology and Aristotelian philosophy. </p><h3><strong>St. Thomas Aquinas on Human Reason and Morality</strong></h3><p>St. Thomas Aquinas, a pivotal figure in medieval scholasticism, expanded upon the ideas of his predecessors, like St. Augustine, by intricately weaving together human reason and divine moral law. Aquinas posited that reason and faith are not antagonistic but complementary forces, each vital to understanding and actualizing the human experience in accordance with God&#8217;s design. At the heart of Aquinas&#8217;s philosophy, detailed in his seminal work <em>Summa Theologica</em>, is the conviction that human reason reflects the divine intellect and is given to humanity to discern the truths of the natural world and comprehend divine laws.</p><p>According to Aquinas, moral clarity is achieved when human reason is correctly applied to divine laws, which are universal and unchanging. This clarity is an academic exercise and a practical guide that enhances human creativity and intellect by aligning them with ultimate truths. When individuals and societies align their actions with these objective moral standards, they not only fulfill their natural purposes but also unlock a higher potential for innovation and reflection. For Aquinas, virtues such as wisdom, justice, courage, and temperance are cultivated through this alignment, each contributing to a holistic enhancement of the individual&#8217;s capacities to think, create, and evaluate.</p><p>St. Thomas Aquinas further elaborated on the role of human reason in engaging with divine moral law. Aquinas posited that human reason is a gift from God that elevates individuals by enabling them to see and enact God&#8217;s will on earth. His teachings suggest that a proper understanding and application of moral law not only refines human nature but also enhances our capacity to engage in higher forms of thinking and creating. As we transition from discussing Augustine&#8217;s foundational views, exploring Aquinas&#8217; integration of reason and morality will provide deeper insights into how abandoning objective moral standards impacts societal order and the intellectual and creative capacities essential for human flourishing.</p><p>Aquinas&#8217;s teachings on the synergy between reason and divine moral law are particularly relevant to understanding the decline in human energy due to moving away from these foundational principles. The abandonment of objective moral laws favoring subjective morality and hedonistic pursuits corresponds with a noticeable degradation in the quality of human thought and creative output. This shift impacts societal structures and diminishes the individual&#8217;s ability to engage in deep, reflective thought, thereby stunting intellectual and cultural development.</p><p>Aquinas&#8217;s framework suggests that the revitalization of human energy hinges on a re-engagement of these timeless truths. By restoring reason&#8217;s role in navigating moral life according to divine law, individuals and societies can recover the vigor necessary for creative and intellectual pursuits. This return to a principled way of living could potentially reverse the intellectual and moral lethargy trends evident in contemporary culture. Next, we will delve into J.D. Unwin&#8217;s anthropological studies, which empirically support these philosophical claims by linking the vitality of civilizations to their adherence to strict moral codes, thereby offering a practical examination of Aquinas&#8217;s theoretical propositions.</p><h3><strong>J.D. Unwin&#8217;s Research on Civilizational Energy</strong></h3><p>J.D. Unwin, a British anthropologist and social scientist, conducted extensive research into the social structures of various civilizations and published his findings in the 1934 book &#8220;Sex and Culture.&#8221; Unwin&#8217;s work is critical for understanding the empirical underpinnings of how sexual behaviors impact societal vitality and longevity. According to his research, there was a direct correlation between the flourishing of civilizations and their strict regulation of sexual conduct.</p><p>Unwin studied about 80  societies and what he labeled as &#8220;six great civilizations&#8221; through their historical records to determine the impact of sexual restraint on societal energy and progress. He found that societies exhibiting higher degrees of sexual restraint in prenuptial and extramarital contexts showed greater social and architectural complexity, increased productivity, and greater artistic and scientific achievement. Conversely, those societies that loosened these strictures typically entered a state of decline within a few generations. Unwin hypothesized that sexual discipline channeled human energy from personal, often hedonistic pursuits toward collective, societal goals, including technological innovation and cultural development.</p><p>Unwin&#8217;s research provides a compelling case study that complements the philosophical insights and moral teachings of St. Augustine and St. Thomas Aquinas. His empirical observations suggest that the decline in human energy marked by diminished creativity, reasoning, and reflective thought can be partially attributed to modern society&#8217;s shift away from strict moral codes and towards greater sexual and moral freedom. While often celebrated as a liberation from traditional constraints, this shift has had unintended dire consequences for societal vigor and individual intellectual energy.</p><p>Unwin&#8217;s conclusions offer a grounding for the discussion on restoring discipline and objective moral guidelines to rejuvenate human creative and intellectual capacities. By examining historical patterns as evidenced in Unwin&#8217;s work, it becomes clear that societal health and energy are contingent upon maintaining a balance between personal freedoms and communal moral standards. Next, we will build on this foundation by exploring G.K. Chesterton&#8217;s critique of modern pride and the loss of humility, further elucidating how these moral and cultural shifts impact the human psyche and societal stability.</p><h3><strong>G.K. Chesterton on Pride and Humility</strong></h3><p>G.K. Chesterton, an influential English writer and Christian apologist, extensively critiqued the cultural shifts towards modern pride, rejecting traditional virtues like humility. In his works, such as &#8220;Orthodoxy&#8221; and &#8220;The Everlasting Man,&#8221; Chesterton argued that humility is foundational to Christian morality and a balanced and reflective life. He saw humility as the virtue that allows individuals to see themselves and the world more clearly, without the distortions of ego.</p><p>Chesterton contended that modern pride&#8212;the excessive belief in one&#8217;s own abilities or importance&#8212;skews perception and judgment. This inflated sense of self leads to various social and personal problems, primarily because it obstructs a truthful engagement with the world. Pride, according to Chesterton, encourages individuals to overestimate their knowledge and understanding, dismissing traditional wisdom and objective moral truths. This hubris can diminish the capacity for critical reflection, as individuals are less likely to question their assumptions or consider perspectives beyond their own.</p><p>Moreover, Chesterton argued that when society collectively turns away from humility and embraces pride, it loses the ability to reason effectively. True reasoning requires acknowledging one&#8217;s limitations and being open to dialogue and correction&#8212;qualities pride actively undermines. The rejection of humility in favor of pride thus not only impacts individual character but also degrades public discourse and the intellectual rigor of society as a whole.</p><p>Connecting these insights to the broader topic of this article, Chesterton&#8217;s critique of modern pride provides a philosophical lens through which to view the current decline in human energy, particularly in the faculties of reason, creation, and reflection. The move away from humility and towards a culture dominated by self-affirmation and subjective truth claims undermines the collective capacity to solve problems and generate new ideas. This cultural shift sets the stage for the next part of this series, &#8220;Part II: The Shift to Subjectivism and Its Consequences.&#8221;</p><p>In Part II, we will delve deeper into how the rise of subjective morality has fragmented the shared ethical foundations that historically supported societal cohesion and collective intellectual endeavors. We will explore the consequences of this fragmentation for individual well-being and societal stability. We will examine how the loss of a common moral language and the rise of individualism impact our ability to address complex challenges together. This examination will underscore the importance of restoring objective moral standards and highlight the critical need for a cultural reevaluation of the values that define our personal and collective lives.</p><div class="subscription-widget-wrap-editor" data-attrs="{&quot;url&quot;:&quot;https://dewilliamsco.substack.com/subscribe?&quot;,&quot;text&quot;:&quot;Subscribe&quot;,&quot;language&quot;:&quot;en&quot;}" data-component-name="SubscribeWidgetToDOM"><div class="subscription-widget show-subscribe"><div class="preamble"><p class="cta-caption">Thanks for reading The Idea Room Newsletter! Subscribe for free to receive new posts and support my work.</p></div><form class="subscription-widget-subscribe"><input type="email" class="email-input" name="email" placeholder="Type your email&#8230;" tabindex="-1"><input type="submit" class="button primary" value="Subscribe"><div class="fake-input-wrapper"><div class="fake-input"></div><div class="fake-button"></div></div></form></div></div>]]>
			</content:encoded>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>
				<![CDATA[The 3 Pillars in the Axis of Societal Corruption]]>
			</title>
			<description>
				<![CDATA[How Corruption in News Media, Social Justice, and Government Destroy Freedom]]>
			</description>
			<link>https://dewilliamsco.substack.com/p/the-3-pillars-in-the-axis-of-societal</link>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">https://dewilliamsco.substack.com/p/the-3-pillars-in-the-axis-of-societal</guid>
			<dc:creator>
				<![CDATA[Daniel Williams]]>
			</dc:creator>
			<pubDate>Wed, 10 Jan 2024 19:14:29 GMT</pubDate>
			<enclosure url="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbf33b5d5-aa35-4296-9e39-2025c7c8177e_1024x1024.webp" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
			<content:encoded>
				<![CDATA[<h2>Summary Overview</h2><p>In today's interconnected world, the intersection of biased news organizations, cancel culture, and government corruption presents complex challenges with far-reaching consequences. Biased news outlets, acting as "Propaganda as a Service," have compromised objective journalism by advancing narratives aligned with specific interests. This shift affects individual freedom and undermines the foundations of democracy, influencing stable families and financial well-being. Concurrently, the evolution of social justice into "Cancel Culture as a Service" has led to punitive practices that restrict free speech and hinder open dialogue. Job loss and reputational damage resulting from cancel culture can impact the stability of families and financial security.</p><p>Furthermore, the concept of "Government as a Service" highlights the pervasive influence of financial contributions on all branches of government, risking corruption and eroding democratic values. When these trends converge, they reinforce one another, potentially distorting public narratives and stifling accountability. However, citizens can counteract these forces through media literacy, political engagement, supporting independent journalism, and advocating for reforms. By taking collective action, society can work to roll back these corrupting forces and promote transparency, accountability, and a more equitable future.</p><div class="subscription-widget-wrap-editor" data-attrs="{&quot;url&quot;:&quot;https://dewilliamsco.substack.com/subscribe?&quot;,&quot;text&quot;:&quot;Subscribe&quot;,&quot;language&quot;:&quot;en&quot;}" data-component-name="SubscribeWidgetToDOM"><div class="subscription-widget show-subscribe"><div class="preamble"><p class="cta-caption">Thanks for reading The Idea Room Newsletter! Subscribe for free to receive new posts and support my work.</p></div><form class="subscription-widget-subscribe"><input type="email" class="email-input" name="email" placeholder="Type your email&#8230;" tabindex="-1"><input type="submit" class="button primary" value="Subscribe"><div class="fake-input-wrapper"><div class="fake-input"></div><div class="fake-button"></div></div></form></div></div><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2 is-viewable-img" target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbf33b5d5-aa35-4296-9e39-2025c7c8177e_1024x1024.webp" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM"><div class="image2-inset"><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbf33b5d5-aa35-4296-9e39-2025c7c8177e_1024x1024.webp 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbf33b5d5-aa35-4296-9e39-2025c7c8177e_1024x1024.webp 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbf33b5d5-aa35-4296-9e39-2025c7c8177e_1024x1024.webp 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbf33b5d5-aa35-4296-9e39-2025c7c8177e_1024x1024.webp 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbf33b5d5-aa35-4296-9e39-2025c7c8177e_1024x1024.webp" width="1024" height="1024" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/bf33b5d5-aa35-4296-9e39-2025c7c8177e_1024x1024.webp&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:1024,&quot;width&quot;:1024,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:&quot;A symbolic representation of the axis of evil in today's interconnected world, featuring three distinct yet interconnected elements. The first element is a biased news outlet represented as a large, distorted satellite dish emitting waves of propaganda, symbolizing compromised objective journalism. The second element is a representation of cancel culture, depicted as a giant, overbearing gavel overshadowing a group of silenced figures with tape over their mouths, symbolizing restricted free speech and punitive practices. The third element is government corruption, illustrated as a grand, opulent building with money flowing into its foundations, representing the influence of financial contributions on government. These three elements are interconnected by chains or links, showing their reinforcement of each other. The background is a dystopian cityscape, hinting at the impact on society, with small figures of citizens holding signs advocating for media literacy, political engagement, and independent journalism, showing the potential for counteraction and reform.&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:false,&quot;topImage&quot;:true,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false,&quot;align&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt="A symbolic representation of the axis of evil in today's interconnected world, featuring three distinct yet interconnected elements. The first element is a biased news outlet represented as a large, distorted satellite dish emitting waves of propaganda, symbolizing compromised objective journalism. The second element is a representation of cancel culture, depicted as a giant, overbearing gavel overshadowing a group of silenced figures with tape over their mouths, symbolizing restricted free speech and punitive practices. The third element is government corruption, illustrated as a grand, opulent building with money flowing into its foundations, representing the influence of financial contributions on government. These three elements are interconnected by chains or links, showing their reinforcement of each other. The background is a dystopian cityscape, hinting at the impact on society, with small figures of citizens holding signs advocating for media literacy, political engagement, and independent journalism, showing the potential for counteraction and reform." title="A symbolic representation of the axis of evil in today's interconnected world, featuring three distinct yet interconnected elements. The first element is a biased news outlet represented as a large, distorted satellite dish emitting waves of propaganda, symbolizing compromised objective journalism. The second element is a representation of cancel culture, depicted as a giant, overbearing gavel overshadowing a group of silenced figures with tape over their mouths, symbolizing restricted free speech and punitive practices. The third element is government corruption, illustrated as a grand, opulent building with money flowing into its foundations, representing the influence of financial contributions on government. These three elements are interconnected by chains or links, showing their reinforcement of each other. The background is a dystopian cityscape, hinting at the impact on society, with small figures of citizens holding signs advocating for media literacy, political engagement, and independent journalism, showing the potential for counteraction and reform." srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbf33b5d5-aa35-4296-9e39-2025c7c8177e_1024x1024.webp 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbf33b5d5-aa35-4296-9e39-2025c7c8177e_1024x1024.webp 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbf33b5d5-aa35-4296-9e39-2025c7c8177e_1024x1024.webp 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbf33b5d5-aa35-4296-9e39-2025c7c8177e_1024x1024.webp 1456w" sizes="100vw" fetchpriority="high"></picture><div class="image-link-expand"></div></div></a></figure></div><h3><strong>1. News Organizations as Propaganda as a Service:</strong></h3><p>In today's media landscape, concerns have arisen about transforming news organizations into what some critics describe as "Propaganda as a Service." This concept suggests that once regarded as impartial sources of information, news outlets have become platforms for promoting biased narratives and advancing specific agendas. The shift towards sensationalism, ideological bias, and the prioritization of profit over journalistic integrity has raised questions about the role of the media in shaping public perception and influencing societal discourse.</p><p>These biased news organizations are often accused of selectively presenting information, downplaying opposing viewpoints, and spreading misinformation or disinformation. This profoundly impacts individual freedom, as citizens rely on a free and independent press to make informed decisions about their lives and the world around them. When news becomes a tool for propaganda, it erodes trust in media and threatens the foundations of a healthy democracy, ultimately affecting stable families and financial well-being.</p><h3><strong>2. Social Justice as Cancel Culture as a Service:</strong></h3><p>The evolution of social justice activism has given rise to what I call "Cancel Culture as a Service." While social justice movements initially aimed to address systemic inequalities and promote fairness, their evolution into cancel culture represents a more punitive and exclusionary approach. Cancel culture often involves the public shaming, ostracization, or boycotting of individuals or organizations deemed to have committed offenses, whether real or perceived.</p><p>This phenomenon encroaches on individual freedom by creating an atmosphere of fear and self-censorship, as people become reluctant to express dissenting opinions for fear of being targeted. Cancel culture can also harm stable families when it leads to job loss or reputational damage, affecting livelihoods and emotional well-being. Balancing the pursuit of social justice with preserving the principles of free speech and open dialogue is a complex challenge in today's online and interconnected world.</p><h3><strong>3. Public Corruption as Government as a Service:</strong></h3><p>The concept of "Government as a Service" paints a troubling picture of a political landscape where all branches of government, including the legislative, executive, and judicial branches, become susceptible to influence from the highest bidder. In this scenario, those with significant financial resources or vested interests can effectively purchase favorable legislation and judicial outcomes, undermining the principles of democracy and accountability.</p><p>The consequences of this system are far-reaching, impacting individual freedom by eroding the notion that the government exists to serve the interests of the people rather than a privileged few. Such corruption can lead to the emergence of an oligarchic society where power is concentrated in a select elite's hands, adversely affecting most of the population's stable families and financial well-being. Addressing this issue requires a concerted effort to combat corruption, increase transparency, and promote political reforms prioritizing the fair representation of all citizens.</p><h2><strong>What happens when these three concepts overlap in society?</strong></h2><p>When the three ideas of biased news organizations (Propaganda as a Service), Cancel Culture as a Service, and government corruption (Government as a Service) overlap in society, it can lead to a complex and concerning set of dynamics that have profound consequences for individuals and the broader community. Here's how these overlapping concepts can manifest and their potential effects:</p><ol><li><p><strong>Reinforcement of Biased Narratives:</strong></p><ul><li><p>Biased news organizations may amplify narratives that align with the interests of corrupt government officials or powerful elites.</p></li><li><p>Cancel culture may be used to silence dissenting voices and stifle criticism of government actions, reinforcing a one-sided narrative.</p></li><li><p>This can result in a distorted public perception of reality, hindering informed decision-making and undermining trust in institutions.</p></li></ul></li><li><p><strong>Chilling Effect on Free Speech:</strong></p><ul><li><p>The convergence of cancel culture and biased news can create a climate of fear, where individuals are hesitant to express diverse opinions or challenge the status quo.</p></li><li><p>The government's role in shaping and regulating speech can further exacerbate this climate, limiting open dialogue and stifling criticism.</p></li><li><p>This stifling of free speech can encroach on individual freedom and hinder societal progress.</p></li></ul></li><li><p><strong>Erosion of Accountability:</strong></p><ul><li><p>A government perceived as serving the interests of a privileged few, with the support of biased media, may escape accountability for corrupt practices and policy decisions.</p></li><li><p>Cancel culture may target those who attempt to expose government corruption, discouraging whistleblowers and activists.</p></li><li><p>The lack of accountability in government can lead to unchecked power, undermining the principles of democracy.</p></li></ul></li><li><p><strong>Threat to Democratic Values:</strong></p><ul><li><p>The combination of biased news, cancel culture, and government corruption can erode democratic values such as transparency, accountability, and equal representation.</p></li><li><p>Citizens may feel disenfranchised and disillusioned, leading to reduced civic engagement and trust in the political system.</p></li><li><p>Stable families and financial wellbeing can suffer when the government prioritizes the interests of elites over the needs of the broader population.</p></li></ul></li><li><p><strong>Calls for Reform and Resistance:</strong></p><ul><li><p>Overlapping concerns may galvanize grassroots movements, civil society, and concerned citizens to push for reforms addressing media bias, cancel culture excesses, and government corruption.</p></li><li><p>Resistance against these trends can manifest in calls for campaign finance reform, media ethics standards, and efforts to promote government transparency.</p></li><li><p>Mobilized efforts to combat these issues can potentially lead to positive changes in society.</p></li></ul></li></ol><p>When these three ideas overlap, they can create a web of challenges that affect not only individual freedom but also stable families and financial wellbeing. Addressing these complex issues requires a multi-pronged approach that involves media accountability, open dialogue, political reforms, and a commitment to upholding traditional western and democratic values.</p><h2>What can we do to roll back these corrupting forces and their multi-decade impact on society?</h2><ol><li><p><strong>Media Accountability and Critical Thinking:</strong></p><ul><li><p>Promote media accountability, transparency, and critical thinking skills among citizens. Encourage people to question the sources of their information and think critically about the narratives presented by the media.</p></li><li><p>Support educational initiatives that teach individuals how to access the trustworthiness of information and its sources, and learn to identify misinformation and disinformation in news reporting.</p></li></ul></li><li><p><strong>Independent Journalism:</strong></p><ul><li><p>Support independent and non-profit journalism organizations committed to objective reporting and investigative journalism. </p></li><li><p>Subscribing to or donating to such outlets can help bolster their impact.</p></li></ul></li><li><p><strong>Demand Accountability:</strong></p><ul><li><p>Hold news organizations accountable for their reporting by fact-checking and providing feedback when inaccuracies or bias are identified.</p></li><li><p>Use social media and public forums to call out instances of biased reporting and demand transparency from media outlets.</p></li></ul></li><li><p><strong>Promote Open Dialogue:</strong></p><ul><li><p>Encourage open dialogue and civil discourse, both online and offline. Promote platforms and initiatives that facilitate constructive discussions on controversial topics.</p></li><li><p>Advocate for universities and educational institutions to protect free speech and academic freedom.</p></li></ul></li><li><p><strong>Political Engagement:</strong></p><ul><li><p>Participate actively in the democratic process by voting, engaging with elected officials, and advocating for campaign finance reform to reduce the influence of money in politics.</p></li><li><p>Support candidates who prioritize transparency, accountability, and policies that benefit the broader population.</p></li></ul></li><li><p><strong>Advocate for Reforms:</strong></p><ul><li><p>Join or support organizations advocating for government and political reforms. These may include efforts to increase transparency, ethics, and anti-corruption measures in government.</p></li><li><p>Lobby for changes in campaign finance laws to reduce the impact of big money in politics.</p></li></ul></li><li><p><strong>Community Building:</strong></p><ul><li><p>Strengthen local communities and networks to foster resilience against divisive forces. Strong, connected communities are better equipped to resist and counteract corruption and misinformation.</p></li></ul></li><li><p><strong>Support Whistleblowers:</strong></p><ul><li><p>Advocate for the protection of whistleblowers who expose government corruption and unethical practices. Whistleblower protection laws can be instrumental in uncovering and addressing systemic issues.</p></li></ul></li><li><p><strong>Legal Actions and Advocacy:</strong></p><ul><li><p>Support legal actions and advocacy efforts aimed at addressing government corruption. This may include participating in or contributing to legal cases that challenge corrupt practices.</p></li></ul></li><li><p><strong>Engage in Peaceful Protests and Activism:</strong></p><ul><li><p>Join or organize peaceful protests, demonstrations, and advocacy campaigns to draw attention to issues related to media bias, cancel culture, and government corruption.</p></li><li><p>Make use of social media and online platforms to raise awareness and mobilize support for causes aligned with combating corruption and promoting accountability.</p></li></ul></li><li><p><strong>Support Legislation and Policy Reforms:</strong></p><ul><li><p>Advocate for and support legislation and policy reforms that promote transparency, ethics, and accountability in government. This may include lobbying for stronger conflict-of-interest laws or ethics commissions.</p></li></ul></li><li><p><strong>Civic Education and Grassroots Movements:</strong></p><ul><li><p>Promote civic education in schools and communities to empower citizens with the knowledge and skills necessary to actively participate in democratic processes.</p></li><li><p>Join or establish grassroots movements dedicated to addressing the root causes of corruption and bias in media and government.</p></li></ul></li></ol><p>Rolling back these corrupting forces will require sustained effort, cooperation, and a commitment to democratic values. Citizens play a crucial role in shaping the direction of their society, and by taking collective action, they can work to counteract the multi-decade impact of these destructive trends.</p><p></p><div class="subscription-widget-wrap-editor" data-attrs="{&quot;url&quot;:&quot;https://dewilliamsco.substack.com/subscribe?&quot;,&quot;text&quot;:&quot;Subscribe&quot;,&quot;language&quot;:&quot;en&quot;}" data-component-name="SubscribeWidgetToDOM"><div class="subscription-widget show-subscribe"><div class="preamble"><p class="cta-caption">Thanks for reading The Idea Room Newsletter! Subscribe for free to receive new posts and support my work.</p></div><form class="subscription-widget-subscribe"><input type="email" class="email-input" name="email" placeholder="Type your email&#8230;" tabindex="-1"><input type="submit" class="button primary" value="Subscribe"><div class="fake-input-wrapper"><div class="fake-input"></div><div class="fake-button"></div></div></form></div></div>]]>
			</content:encoded>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>
				<![CDATA[Investing in Education and Examining the Massive Amount of Student Debt Impacting the U.S.]]>
			</title>
			<description>
				<![CDATA[Getting to the Bottom of the Student Loan Debt Crisis &#8212; and the Solutions Necessary to Correct Course]]>
			</description>
			<link>https://dewilliamsco.substack.com/p/investing-in-education-and-examining</link>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">https://dewilliamsco.substack.com/p/investing-in-education-and-examining</guid>
			<dc:creator>
				<![CDATA[Daniel Williams]]>
			</dc:creator>
			<pubDate>Mon, 19 Sep 2022 19:56:13 GMT</pubDate>
			<enclosure url="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd9bdab4d-d722-4d75-bff9-27f16320c245_4496x3000.jpeg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
			<content:encoded>
				<![CDATA[<p>Second only to home mortgages, <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/select/student-debt-hits-another-record-high-what-you-need-to-know/">student loans are one of the two largest consumer debt categories</a> in the U.S. As of 2021, student loan debt totaled <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2022/03/24/heres-what-you-need-to-know-about-your-student-loans-before-its-too-late.html">nearly $1.75 trillion</a>, a growth of 80% over the last decade. So naturally, much of the media attention is on the demographics of debt holders, as women are more likely than men to carry student loan debt &#8212; even more so with Black (31%) and Hispanic (19%) women.</p><p>While certainly cause for concern, the focus is somewhat misplaced. The decisions, policies, and other factors that led to this massive problem deserve greater scrutiny, as we're effectively trading present-day profits for the prosperity of future generations.</p><div class="subscription-widget-wrap-editor" data-attrs="{&quot;url&quot;:&quot;https://dewilliamsco.substack.com/subscribe?&quot;,&quot;text&quot;:&quot;Subscribe&quot;,&quot;language&quot;:&quot;en&quot;}" data-component-name="SubscribeWidgetToDOM"><div class="subscription-widget show-subscribe"><div class="preamble"><p class="cta-caption">Thanks for reading The Tech Room Newsletter! Subscribe for free to receive new posts and support my work.</p></div><form class="subscription-widget-subscribe"><input type="email" class="email-input" name="email" placeholder="Type your email&#8230;" tabindex="-1"><input type="submit" class="button primary" value="Subscribe"><div class="fake-input-wrapper"><div class="fake-input"></div><div class="fake-button"></div></div></form></div></div><div class="captioned-image-container"><figure><a class="image-link image2 is-viewable-img" target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd9bdab4d-d722-4d75-bff9-27f16320c245_4496x3000.jpeg" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM"><div class="image2-inset"><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd9bdab4d-d722-4d75-bff9-27f16320c245_4496x3000.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd9bdab4d-d722-4d75-bff9-27f16320c245_4496x3000.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd9bdab4d-d722-4d75-bff9-27f16320c245_4496x3000.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd9bdab4d-d722-4d75-bff9-27f16320c245_4496x3000.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd9bdab4d-d722-4d75-bff9-27f16320c245_4496x3000.jpeg" width="1456" height="972" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/d9bdab4d-d722-4d75-bff9-27f16320c245_4496x3000.jpeg&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:972,&quot;width&quot;:1456,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:3201081,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/jpeg&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:false,&quot;topImage&quot;:true,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false,&quot;align&quot;:null}" class="sizing-normal" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd9bdab4d-d722-4d75-bff9-27f16320c245_4496x3000.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd9bdab4d-d722-4d75-bff9-27f16320c245_4496x3000.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd9bdab4d-d722-4d75-bff9-27f16320c245_4496x3000.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd9bdab4d-d722-4d75-bff9-27f16320c245_4496x3000.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw" fetchpriority="high"></picture><div class="image-link-expand"></div></div></a></figure></div><p></p><p>Consider the interest rates charged for student loans. They're incredibly high and <a href="https://www.bankrate.com/loans/student-loans/federal-student-loan-rate-hike-2022-2023/#:~:text=Federal%20student%20loan%20interest%20rates%20are%20set%20to%20rise%20for,7.54%20percent%20for%20PLUS%20loans.">set to get even higher this summer</a>. For instance, federal Stafford loan interest rates for undergrads will increase from 3.73% to 4.99%. Interest rates for grad students will also see a hike, rising from 5.28% to 6.54%. Students interested in a federal PLUS loan aren't exempt, either. They can now expect an interest rate of 7.54%, rather than the 6.28% in previous years. As a country, it's almost as if we treat education as an interest-bearing commodity instead of what it truly is &#8212; an investment in vital skills for the benefit of our national interests and the ability to compete globally.</p><p><strong>Not an Accident in the Making</strong></p><p>Beyond interest rates, we can trace a large part of the growing student loan debt problem back to the definitions of <em>education</em> and <em>skills development</em>. They now appear to mean two different things. In the past, education consisted of learning skills and preparing for a career that would allow individuals to reach their <strong>endless potential</strong> and compete in the national or global marketplace. Education today often means that students spend several years having fun with friends at a college or university and walk away with a degree (if they stay and graduate).</p><p>Complicating matters further are policies, many of which allow none of the parties involved to have any real "skin in the game." All you need is to look at the lending process to see what I mean. During a typical loan transaction, outside of education, the lender will usually assess the repayment risk and ability of the borrower to repay. However, in the case of education loans, the lender faces almost no chance of default because borrowers can't discharge student loans with bankruptcy. Therefore, it doesn't matter to lenders if the market or career prospects within a given major are low. They will get their money back &#8212; and then some &#8212; no matter if the borrower graduates or ends up in their chosen career.</p><p>Perhaps both public and private lenders should make these types of analyses available to borrowers. Likewise, schools should do more in the area of providing practical information on study majors, career prospects, and market projections to students and families. But why should they? Little if any incentives are tied to the success of graduates outside the institution's grounds. The schools get paid regardless of which field of study is selected. No one is <strong>focusing on the best interest </strong>of the student.</p><p>Because students and families often didn't have the information necessary to make sound decisions regarding education, many opted for college when a different path had the potential of netting a better outcome. Others selected a college that lacked the right resources, faculty, or training. Then, some chose a major that did not give them the skills to compete nationally or globally. Collectively, these factors contribute to the massive and continually rising student loan debt crisis.</p><p><strong>Requiring a Collective Fix</strong></p><p>With so many parties involved in the crisis, it will take a collective effort to correct course &#8212; first and foremost being policymakers. Those at the national, state, and local levels need to establish policies clearly outlining how education is an investment in the nation's future and its ability to compete worldwide. And they need to include multiple strategies detailing the skills and capabilities that the U.S. needs in the upcoming years to modernize and maintain our infrastructure and innovate in key and emerging industries.</p><p>Better yet, allocate education investment funding in these critical areas and make the money available to all public colleges and universities. Consider allotting additional public funds to institutions when their graduates can find employment in their major within six months of graduation. Then, if graduates maintain employment at 12, 18, or 24 months after graduation, offer additional funds or incentives to the school. That will certainly up their skin in the game and all but guarantee <strong>better experiences</strong>. I am aware of one <a href="https://youtube.com/shorts/S4g0pKrecgM?feature=share">school in Texas</a> successfully experimenting with this model.</p><p>Colleges and universities will also play a direct role in the collective fix. For one, these institutions must do a much better job aligning with the education needs of students and families. They also need to reestablish the link between education and skills development. For example, some schools are developing and expanding relationships with employers to co-create more practical curricula so that students graduate with hands-on experience and skills needed in the workforce. Most importantly, schools need to guide students into majors that coincide with their talents, their interests, and our nation's strategic needs.</p><p>Lenders, too, should take on more responsibility. If we do retain the student loan approach to paying for college, lenders must help students minimize the risks associated with loans. They can do this by providing analysis, reports, and recommendations on schools, majors, skills, careers, expected salaries, lifetime earnings, and so on. This information will give students the best chance to make good decisions and increase the probability of <strong>ensuring success</strong> in life.</p><p>Beyond these parties, students and families must become more informed. A four-year degree isn't the best path to success for everyone. Community college, trade skills and apprenticeships are all valuable and viable options &#8212; and are, in fact, very respectable in this day and age. There's also an emerging trend that some call "new collar" jobs, where people gain tech skills without incurring the massive debt associated with a four-year degree. The options include coding boot camps and online cloud computing/development certifications on platforms such as AWS, Azure, Google, Salesforce, and others.</p><p><strong>How We Go About Correcting Course</strong></p><p>The public sector must change its approach to education. Currently, the federal government sets education policies and provides loans without a coherent national strategy. Multiple government agencies publish reports on necessary skills in STEM, trades, infrastructure, and national security that the U.S. will need in the coming years and decades. However, policies and incentives rarely align with the data.</p><p>The public sector can begin by redefining education as an investment portfolio to achieve national interest objectives. The following can help move the nation in the right direction:</p><ul><li><p>Establish a strategic vision of the skills necessary to compete globally over the next five, 10, and 20 years. Assess the impact of changes in <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SNCo-f2xJVU">demographics</a>, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7QvtSbsX8Xk">deglobalization</a>, and new technologies such as <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7Pq-S557XQU">AI and automation</a>.</p></li><li><p>Develop an education portfolio strategy in partnership with the private sector, detailing the key industries and skills needed.</p></li><li><p>Enter <strong>partnerships</strong> with colleges, universities, community colleges, and trade schools that meet necessary skills development requirements to receive strategic funding. Also, distribute this information to high schools and other organizations that work with students and families.</p></li><li><p>Set a federal policy to fund only the skills and education aligned with the strategic vision. While anyone is free to study and major in anything outside the national strategy, it won't be tuition-free and must be funded out-of-pocket or via private loans.</p></li><li><p>Reassess the national education strategy every two to three years to ensure we're developing the right skills and keeping pace with the rapid technological changes.</p></li></ul><p>The student loan debt crisis won't be fixed overnight. However, we must do something if we ever hope to get graduates out from under the weight of the money still owed &#8212; or yet to be owed. It will take a collective effort, but we can solve the problem and prepare the next generations for an American 21st century.</p><div class="subscription-widget-wrap-editor" data-attrs="{&quot;url&quot;:&quot;https://dewilliamsco.substack.com/subscribe?&quot;,&quot;text&quot;:&quot;Subscribe&quot;,&quot;language&quot;:&quot;en&quot;}" data-component-name="SubscribeWidgetToDOM"><div class="subscription-widget show-subscribe"><div class="preamble"><p class="cta-caption">Thanks for reading The Tech Room Newsletter! Subscribe for free to receive new posts and support my work.</p></div><form class="subscription-widget-subscribe"><input type="email" class="email-input" name="email" placeholder="Type your email&#8230;" tabindex="-1"><input type="submit" class="button primary" value="Subscribe"><div class="fake-input-wrapper"><div class="fake-input"></div><div class="fake-button"></div></div></form></div></div>]]>
			</content:encoded>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>